[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
foreign
I hope you are all doing very well and
uh let us see as usual before we begin
let's see who all is on The Telecast
right now I can see parth avijit Rohit
ayush samarth Nandan auspicious doomsday
CP Verma Abhishek the guy siddhant
swap nanil Purna Aditi YK pratham ayush
foreign
shubham
and lots and lots of other people good
evening good at all of you wherever you
are I hope you're doing very well and
thank you for being on the show so uh
today we will take questions that you
all have asked in the uh comments and
hopefully that will Encompass all the
questions that everybody hopefully most
of the questions that people have asked
you know the major ones the ones that
are of importance right now uh so where
shall We Begin let us begin with
something that we have spoken about in
the past but uh let's take it to the
logical inclusion and uh let's go to the
UK shall we
okay so I've got a couple of questions
one is by doing Johan the other one is
by Tejas Rishi sunak is proving himself
more British than the actual British
it's not a problem if he's working in
favor of his country but taking an
anti-india step by appointing swella
what do you think enthusia says what's
your opinion about is it in the Indian
interest that an Indian origin person is
the PM of Youth of the UK how should we
see it so I think this will be the last
time I answer these questions I have
obviously taken these questions before
but let's let's take it one more time
because this is a new development has
recently been appointed selected
whatever as the prime minister of the UK
and lots of people in India naturally
are rejoicing yeah great for us is the
prime minister Indian origin guy first
ever first ever Indian origin person if
I am not mistaken first ever Hindu and
so on so forth Indians are very happy so
with that in mind these are good
questions
is it in the Indian interest that an
Indian origin person is the prime
minister of the UK
the prime minister of the UK it doesn't
matter what is his or her ethnicity his
or her gender or whatever else their job
is to serve the interests of their
nation that that is the that is the
specification that's the job description
right it's to lead the country forward
in the right direction whatever is best
from the perspective of the UK's
National interest and do everything
for the UK to benefit the UK that's the
that's their entire job description and
that it's limited to that so uh
so it doesn't really make any difference
to India whether it's it's
who was it last time Liz trust was it
Liz truss was there for a few weeks or
if it's somebody else it makes no
difference for for us yeah of course one
could argue that if if it is as opposed
to somebody like uh let's what's his
name that the who's the mayor of London
Sajid Khan Pakistani origin so I would
say that when it comes to these
possibilities of of having two
candidates A and B candidate a is Russia
candidate B is let's say Sajid Sajid
Javed or whatever his name is the
current mayor of London I think overall
it's it's somewhat better for us if it's
an Indian origin person as opposed to a
Pakistani origin person in the prime
minister's position obviously Pakistani
origin people are also Indian origin
people because 70 years ago there was no
Pakistan and so we know that so that's
without the point so overall it's it's
uh it could have been worse uh they
could have appointed somebody who is out
and out anti-india as opposed to that
we've got somebody who is at least a
Indian origin person so yeah from that
perspective it's fine but otherwise it
makes no real difference to India right
I've spoken in the past about the the
fact that there are various CEOs of
various Fortune 500 companies in the US
lots of these people are Indian
Norwegian people and does that benefit
India in any way whatsoever it does not
it does not benefit India to have or an
Indian origin person as the head of
whatever Fortune 500 company whatever
Hmong company or whatever you want to
call it yeah it makes no difference to
India it doesn't benefit India in any
way uh they serve their their company
their corporation in this of the nation
and they are all U.S citizens in the
case of racism he's a UK citizen so he's
gonna serve the UK
so uh from that perspective it doesn't
really make much of a difference and the
real question you do ask yourself is
does the UK prime minister have any
actual real power these days Prime
Ministers are elected not selected you
have general elections once in a while
the last general election was one uh by
the current ruling party under the
stewardship or leadership of Boris
Johnson Boris Johnson has been removed
in a coup because of whatever reason the
reasons don't matter has been removed
then you had the what's her name list
trust who let's trusts who was in power
Who was appointed who was put on the on
the hot seat for a while and she's gone
now because so you know what uh I'm not
really sure how much real genuine power
the UK prime minister actually holds
power is is something that's mysterious
power is something that people don't
really understand power
comes from a variety of things and the
UK prime minister doesn't really have
much power it's clear that uh their
appointment is something that is done by
an unknown group of people you could say
it's it's the political party they
belong to and they decide that so and so
leader is not performing well we're
going to pull her down and we're going
to appoint somebody else in their place
but
but then if that is the case then why
wasn't Boris Johnson made the PM again I
mean he was in power for a while he did
not perform terribly he certainly
performed better than what's her name
what's her name right let's trust and he
was supposed to throw his hat in the
ding and the last moment he somehow
pulled it out
this is the first time they say he ever
pulled out of anything you know that's
what they say about Boris Johnson so
so yeah it's mysterious what made him do
that so clearly the levels of Power are
being controlled from well somewhere
else
and I think we can all guess whether
what direction it comes from yeah so
anyhow so the UK prime minister doesn't
really have any real power and they
essentially do as they are told I think
I'm sure it will make some people
unhappy and they will Express their
unhappiness in the comments which is
fine I'm perfectly fine with that but
it's clear the UK prime minister ship is
a revolving door just like what they've
done to Japan yeah the Japanese prime
minister comes and goes apart from
Shinzo Abe nobody lost it and we we know
what happened very unfortunate anyhow so
uh
well he's just he's just a figurehead
right uh now the question is he's
proving himself more British than the
actual British he appointed he took an
anti-india step by appointing
reappointing swella braver man to the
possession of the Home Secretary which
is the the British equivalent of the
home minister so India's home minister
is Mr amitsha and in the UK it's uh it's
uh this lady uh swella Braverman who is
of Indian origin and uh
and she was the the Home Secretary under
the previous prime minister as well Liz
truss and it was swella's resignation
that set in set in the motion this
domino effect which concluded the next
day Itself by Liz truss herself having
to resign from from Office one day after
she said that she will fight yeah and
then
to the same position where she clearly
herself said that she made a big mistake
you know that sort of thing so it's
clear that it's not Rishi sunak who has
appointed her she has been asked he has
been directed to appoint swella
Braverman to this position because of
whatever reason we don't know what the
reasons are so it's not his choice
please understand certain things my dear
friends
[Music]
whoever is the UK prime minister in the
2020s that person he or she doesn't
really have any real power they don't
even get to choose they will get to
select some minor positions but the main
positions will be filled by by well the
decisions will be taken elsewhere right
so it's clearly the powers that that be
that have decided that that uh swella
Braverman should be the Home Secretary
is it an anti-india step step well the
UK isn't an important Nation it's simply
a proxy of a much larger power that's
all the UK is so what happens in the UK
is not of great consequence to the world
yes India and the UK are are negotiating
this Free Trade Agreement and this Visa
deal and all that which is okay which is
okay which
will matter to some people but overall
from the Indian economic perspective
National interest perspective it is not
in the long term in the larger scheme of
things a very important thing what is
really important is how India deals uh
approaches its dealings with the
superpower the United States and other
nations that are important right the UK
is a peripheral Nation the UK is not
even a second great world power anymore
it's a proxy it's a wasall of the US so
uh yes this lady has a shorter shorter
mouth of multiple times she herself is
of Indian origin both parents are of
Indian origin right so she's 100 pure
blood Indian and she has been saying
things that are well well kind of
derogatory towards Indians that Indians
have a habit of overstaying their UK
visas and all that well um what about
the fact that the the British overstayed
in India more than 250 years I mean what
business did they have being in India
right so uh anyhow that's that's one
rebuttal you could offer to her if you
are active on social media and so on but
that's fine
so uh
she is not somebody who really matters
right she will herself as the Home
Secretary see there are four great
offices in the UK one of which is the
Home Secretary the other is the defense
secretary the chancellor of the
exchecker and the Prime Minister these
four are the four Great offices that's
what they are called today they they are
no longer great or they are no longer
important because the power is lies
entirely elsewhere so it doesn't matter
once again whether swella braver man is
the Home Secretary or some unknown other
person is the home security it doesn't
matter anymore these are just
figureheads and the real power the real
decision making is elsewhere so it's not
an anti-india step a step yeah maybe
it's it's a it's designed to to make the
UK government look balanced and and even
though you've appointed an Indian origin
person as the PM we have upon a
vocal India critic as the home minister
so you know balancing it's a lot of
messaging and all that at the end of the
day these people don't really make any
real decisions so it doesn't really
matter so uh my opinion about Richardson
is that it's okay it's it's nice it
could have been worse it could have been
a Pakistani origin person or something
like that or somebody is repeatedly
anti-india or it could have been swella
herself as a prime minister so compared
to that it's it looks nicer to have
someone of
background as a prime minister but it
doesn't really matter and uh
is he more British than the actual
British no he's just British and he's
just just doing what he's told that's
what every UK PM does whether it's Boris
Johnson whether it was titties or may
whether it was what's her name Liz Truss
I'm sorry I don't mean to be disparaging
towards her I'm sure she's a competent
politician and a nice person possibly I
don't know I don't know much about her
she was hardly there and so on so it
doesn't matter who the prime minister is
they just do what they're told the UK
prime ministership is not important
anymore so that's that's my opinion
about this
okay some more questions about uh Mr
Richardson Rahul Singh says
on Friday today's Sunday right yeah on
Friday just a couple of days ago on
Friday gave his first prime minister's
questions and the way he gave answers to
the questions it looked like he isn't it
for the long run what are my thoughts
about this and audiences is it possible
that under rishis or not the UK could
start pursuing an independent foreign
policy if yes what will the will will be
the consequences
so the first question is about
the fact that Rishi Suna gave his first
prime minister's questions pmq they call
it and the way he answered the questions
it looked like he is in it for the long
run so once again we are prioritizing
spectacle or substance
how many times must I have said this and
I'm gonna keep repeating it but because
I'm sure there are newer viewers who
have not been here before and so on
words don't matter how you speak doesn't
matter how you portray yourself and what
spectacle you create doesn't matter it
is the actions that matter he's been in
office for what less than a week three
days two days half an hour I don't know
what how long has been office and yes he
he fielded the pmq very well he gave
very good questions and he looked like
he means business and it looked like it
looked like he's in it for the for the
long run he could the rug could be
pulled out from under his feet tomorrow
next week
next evening
the real power lies somewhere else
doesn't really have any real power he
will be allowed to remain in office as
long as he serves
the powers that be
and he is a faithful and and assiduous
servant to their cause right that's all
it is so as long as it fulfills the the
directions that are given to him and it
does a good competent job at it he'll be
allowed to be the Prime Minister and yet
I'm not sure even if he does a good job
he'll be allowed to stay for too long
because any politician who stays for too
long for a certain period of time in a
leadership position gains some real
power and that is always dangerous when
you are
a remote controlling of a South State
you'd never want any of their
politicians even if they have been
appointed by you yourself you never want
them to stay in power for too long it
should always be a revolving door uh uh
a pole position prime minister should
presentership whatever right so if I am
running if I am a superpower and I am
remote controlling of assault State I
have appointed their leader Prime
Minister President duties I don't want
that person to stay in power for too
long first of all I will not appoint a
person who is extremely competent and
who has some real leadership qualities I
will Upon A person who will be a good
CEO but not a good founder
there are many Indian CEOs in Silicon
Valley in in the in the U.S fortunate
500 companies right so if I am a
superpower I will appoint a person who
will be a good servant but not be a good
leader they will do exactly what I tell
them and even if they are they do the
job well I will not allow them to remain
in power for too long because if they
have been in power for Beyond a certain
period of time they will actually gain
some real leadership
somebody or some real power because that
is the nature of power somebody who's in
a leadership position for a certain
period of time gains genuine power
through all the contacts they make and
all the that's how it works yeah that's
that's how power works so I don't see uh
yeah sure he is in the in it for the
long run I I suspect he may last us
significantly longer perhaps perhaps he
he may last longer than his predecessor
what's her name Liz dress yes for sure I
I am pretty much sure that he may last
longer than her yeah I may be wrong but
I think he'll last longer than her but
I'm not sure how long he will be allowed
to last will he last as long as Boris
Johnson lasted very last as long as
what's her name there is a male lasted
or anybody else we don't know so it is
likely that he will last much longer
than Liz Truss but will he have any
actual power and will he be the main
person doing the real decision making
that is not quite the case the second
question is um
is it possible that under races or not
the UK could start pursuing an
independent foreign policy that is
impossible
the moment
deviates from the script he's gonna be
gone
that's how it goes he is gonna
not deviate from the script the script
will be handed over to him every single
day and he's gonna play the role there
are various such people who play the
role of Prime Minister President in
various parts of the world I think you
may have heard of some some people who
use green screens and who
who are not where they seem to be and so
on so these people are handed out
scripts every single day they are told
what to do and what to say and what
statements to make and what
pronouncements to make and what
Communications to put out and there's a
team around the resistance people and
they stick to the script the moment they
deviate from the script
they're gone they're done
so um I do not see Rishi sunak ever
pursuing an independent foreign policy
for the UK he has auditioned multiple
times for the role of the chief servant
of the superpower and now that is got it
he's gonna do his best to stay in power
as long as he can and he can only do
that by sticking to the script that's
given to him so I do not see Rishi Suna
pursuing an independent foreign policy
if yes what are the consequences he'll
be gone in half an hour
removed from the prime minister's
position and he will never get any big
position again if he does that so that
is how it goes and that's the simple
fact about the UK or about Australia or
New Zealand or Canada or any of the
various uh big and small U.S visal
states that's simply how it goes
all right this is a lengthy question by
harita
uh everyone says winter is coming
implying that it could it would hurt
Europe and benefit Russia what will be
the effects of winter households will
need to spend more to hit their homes
which is that much is understood what
will be the consequences of it
economically and politically and how
will it all affect the war how does the
winter affect corporates and factories
Beyond needing to heat their office
spaces India has been successfully
providing various subsidies for years
now why can't the European Union provide
energy subsidies I know it would hurt
the other nations of the EU if only one
nation like Germany does it but why
can't they work together to provide the
subsidies in their all in all their
Nations and do it smartly unlike in
Britain
do you think Putin underestimated global
warning warming it used to snow for
multiple weeks in Germany and France
earlier but the past few years so only
mild snowfall for one or two days what
happens if the winter is not as severe
as expected okay a whole bunch of
questions and before I answer this let's
also put this on the record this is by
yesha living in Germany I can confirm
what you're saying once per month energy
contract was 60 Euros now it's 150 Euros
good God that's like two and a half
times yeah uh groceries and everything
else is getting costlier once we were
spending once we are spending 150 to 200
Euros for grocery per month now it's
more like 300 Euros it's uh starting in
in the beginning everyone was supporting
the government for the Ukraine vote now
they have started commending the
government uh I mean yeah okay and also
common people have started to understand
Uncle Sam's strategy but they can't do
anything as the US is still present in
Germany the US is very much present in
Germany and people who live in Germany
and who have been there for some time
actually understand that okay so yes so
this is uh the the this is a
a ground report so to more or less from
somebody who's actually staying there
now let's go back to the questions asked
by harita
um
uh so what will the effects of winter be
households will need to spend more to
heat their homes right so when it comes
to Heat Winter if you look at the energy
graph of the of Europe how much energy
how much coal and gas is is consumed and
how much energy is consumed it always
spikes in Winter if you look at a
five-year Trend you will always see the
highest consumption of energy happening
in Winter because it's very cold right
in various parts of Europe it snows it
freezes it goes to below zero degrees
Celsius and you need to heat your homes
otherwise gonna freeze in your house if
you're if the temperature inside your
house is minus 10 degrees Celsius it's
hard to survive and stay alive one night
right so you'd need energy you need fuel
and you know what's happening for the
past 15 20 years the Russians have been
providing Europe with unlimited support
almost unlimited supplies of energy
let's go to the map and let's take a
look at uh how it is so we have been
talking about what's it called called uh
we've been talking about node stream
node stream is not the only pipeline
that connects Russian energy supplies to
Europe
there are lots and lots of various
pipelines large and small that uh that
Supply Russian gas
to Europe and Europe was benefiting from
these more or less unlimited supplies of
gas and that's how Europe was uh
uh that's that's something that powered
the European economy for the longest
time
and that's what powered the the heating
and the warming of European homes all
these years and now that the war has
happened and the Russians have more or
less Switched Off the the supply of gas
it's a big problem so Russia has an
enormous amount of territory and it it
the the so-called Heartland
or pivot area from in in terms of
makinder's Heartland theory it it
essentially holds nearly if not more
than half of the world's resources half
of the world's resources of of anything
you can imagine all kinds of Natural
Resources right uh it uh raw materials
petroleum Metals uh oil gas minerals
agriculture whatever you you need you
know to sustain a nation and to sustain
a large military and the the Russians
have been supplying Europe with this and
you need this energy to run Industries
not only for heating home but to run
Industries whether you are manufacturing
steel whether you are manufacturing
chemicals whether you are running
whatever industry it is whether the the
Germans uh their number one industry is
car manufacturing isn't it so to do that
you need large amounts of energy and
and Europe was consuming almost
unlimited amounts of energy from Russia
now that's stopped right now it's not
like the Europeans are gonna all die and
freeze but it's gonna it's gonna raise
it's this the price of energy is
skyrocketing
and I think during winter Russian homes
consume more than
compared to Summer let's say uh Europe
consumes 50 to 70 more energy the
European homes consume that much more
energy and now when you are facing a
resource crunch a gas crunch if you are
to
ensure that all every house in Europe
gets the amount of air gas it needs to
to for fuel for cooking for energy for
heating and all that then you're gonna
have to divert some some of that away
from the industry
or you have only a limited amount of
energy and the prices will go much
higher and then there'll be energy
rationing uh people will be asked not to
use the heaters at certain times of the
day in the in the daylight hours or
whatever it's gonna be a very tough
winter it's gonna it's gonna
it's going to affect the industrial
output of the European uh powerhouses
industrial powerhouses France and
Germany are the main two Nations Germany
is the industrial Heartland of Europe
it's going to affect Germany
significantly yeah uh and so it's going
to affect uh corporations it's going to
affect factories uh and subsidies yes
well when you have limited supplies of
energy you can subsidize energy but then
what if you run out of energy that's the
thing Germany seems to have stored a
reasonable amount of energy gas or
whatever it is and they are giving
subsidies but is every European nation
in a position to do that in India we are
not facing a resource crunch thus far
we're not facing a petroleum crunch or
any other any fuel Crunch and that's why
India can provide subsidies in in
various ways you know India during the
corona whereas pandemic provided almost
more or less free uh food grains to a
significant amount of the population we
did that for like a significant period
of time nearly two years and that's why
India that's how India was able to tide
over that crisis
but um but is Europe in a position to do
that it's not just about okay we have
the money so we will give subsidies is
it's about do we have the energy
supplies do we have the the natural
resources do we have the the gas that's
needed to power the whole of Europe for
the entire duration of the winter
um and so that's that's the current rub
that that the European nations are
facing now the Germans have decided to
give subsidies but will all other
nations be able to follow suit uh it is
uh unlikely I would say if it happens
it's great I will be happy for the
people of Europe but what's happening is
that it may be very difficult now about
global warming it used to snow for
multiple weeks in Germany and France
earlier now the past few years we've
only seen mild snowfall see global
warming obviously is a thing I don't
think Putin has underestimated global
warming I don't think truthin
underestimates anything he's not a
Madman or a crazy person he's a very
rational actor he thinks with uh with uh
all contingencies in mind that's how you
plan ahead for uh when you're running a
whole nation
um there are see you can't always
control the weather you can't always
predict the weather I mean I was in
Northern India just uh 10 days ago it
was freezing there yeah in some parts of
the in ladakh it's like minus seven
minus 10 degrees in October itself when
it's supposed to be Autumn not winter so
the opposite of global warming also
happens you never know what's going to
happen right so there was unseasonable
unseasonal snowfall everywhere you know
very cold temperatures so the same thing
could happen in Europe I mean we do have
weather modeling and predictions and all
that but at the end of the day you don't
know so I don't think global warming has
become that severe yet we still don't
know how this winter is going to be
and you so um the winter is gonna be
cold it may not snow that much perhaps
but it's certainly going to be cold yeah
and the objective is to wear the people
down it's not the objective I don't
think is to kill people I don't think
the people of Europe will die as a
result of this but lots of people will
indeed suffer and the question they're
going to ask themselves is why are we
doing this to ourselves why are these
why are our governments doing this to us
this is not our conflict it's not our
war why are we suffering we are supposed
to we have been imposing these sanctions
on the Russians and the objective is to
make Russia suffer but why are we
suffering are we Russians I think that's
a joke that Mr Putin cracked recently
right so if this persists for multiple
months it's gonna create a lot of
resentment for the governments in Europe
among their population among their
citizenry and that's gonna be make it
very hard for the governments in Europe
to continue along the same lines
so the cold months are October November
December January February until February
uh some parts of March as well March is
when spring comes in yeah so things get
better in March so you've got a
significant period of time like four
months
and about four months of time in which
it's going to be really cold it's going
to get really really difficult for
Europe so yeah so uh I think Mr Burton
is banking on the fact that there's
going to be a lot of uh pushback a lot
of recent men among the populations in
Europe against the policies that their
governments have been made to dig
and uh yeah and obviously there'll be a
plan beyond that also from Putin's
perspective once spring comes in what's
going to be the plan for for Ukraine I
mean is he gonna
ask his soldiers his his forces to
hunker down to to infringe themselves at
whatever position they've got right now
in winter is there going to be a winter
offensive we don't know yeah but from
the energy perspective I think this is
the the plan that he has got for the
next four months to make this uh this
entire conflict extremely unpopular
in Europe among the people of Europe and
that would make it hard for the
governments to keep on Towing the the
NATO line right because it doesn't
benefit the nation let's say from from
the perspective of let's say France
although from from the perspective of
what other Nation do we have Netherlands
Belgium Denmark whatever it is right uh
from their perspective what are their
citizens gaining out of all this they
are suffering they are made to suffer
from multiple months the the groceries
are disappearing there are no more
heaters available and so on there there
is this resource crunch that all the
people are facing for to what effect for
what purpose how does it benefit the
common man woman and child right how
does it benefit the nation
so that's the kind of recent when Mr
Putin wants to create he's got this
trump card winter is always the Russian
trump card and I'm sure there's got
plans beyond that so that is what's
happening uh I don't think it's that
easy to just provide subsidies because
you need the energy you need the
resources you need the gas or or
whatever it is and many of the European
nations have been shutting down their
nuclear power plants Germans were doing
this now they're reopening cool power
plants and all that it's muddled
thinking
and this this crisis is is plunging
Europe headlong into into a slow
disaster it's not good yeah and who's
benefiting it's not the Europeans who
are benefiting from this
so that's the thing so that's the game
Mr Putin is playing that's how it goes
in war there is no nothing is unfair in
in war all options are on the cards and
that's what's happening uh so yeah so
that's what's happening in Europe
okay mayork says as you said in one of
your recent videos Pakistan is back back
in the U.S Camp so is there a
possibility of an upcoming
india-pakistan War as the U.S would want
to
hamper India's rapid growth in a bid to
become a top three or even top two
nation in the world
yes I I spoke about this yesterday
itself in the in episode 10 of the
Indian interest that uh Pakistan is now
fully
in the U.S Camp so for the past 10 years
or so Pakistan has been uh in the
Chinese Camp Pakistan and China have
been calling each other the iron
Brothers right the iron Brothers we will
be together through thick and thin and
all that well the iron has melted now
yeah the iron iron has evaporated
Pakistan is fully back in the U.S Camp
Pakistan is now a full-fledged U.S
basala state the same way it used to be
in the 20th century right
in the U.S
can throw way more money at the
Pakistani General than the Chinese can
and the U.S also have other ways of
coercing the pakistanis I mean in the
past there who what's his name Richard
Armitage had once threatened Pakistan I
think in the 20th century in the late
20th century that if they did not uh tow
the U.S line he would uh send he would
bomb them back to the Stone Age so this
this carrots in their sticks in the U.S
no the Americans know how to use that so
the pakistanis are back to being the U.S
facade the U.S well yeah let's use the
wasal word nothing was nothing stronger
than that
yeah so the pakistanis are back in the
U.S Camp so the Chinese have lost all
control of Pakistan that's to be
understood and there's going to be lots
of repercussions of that in the coming
days
um
so the question is about India Pakistan
will India Pakistan could be could there
be in the future in india-pakistan war
because the U.S would want to hamper
India's rapid growth
the U.S certainly sees India as a
long-term adversary the U.S doesn't want
I mean India has the potential to become
the number two even the number one
economy in the world certainly number
three in the next five ten years India
will definitely become the number three
economy of the world no one's going to
be able to stop that the real question
is will it be able to surpass China in
the next 30 Years yeah in the next 20
years or come close to China and India
has the resources India has the Manpower
India has a talent India has everything
it's at its disposal to be able to do
that so as a superpower as a major power
as a great power you think long term you
don't think short term you don't think
what's going to happen next year what's
gonna happen the next three years you
think about what's going to happen in
the next 50 years you look at you look
at geopolitics from a 20-year 50-year
100 Year Horizon and you want to ensure
that your Supremacy your hegemony
remains and stays in place that long so
from that perspective India is a future
long-term adversary for the US it's a
it's it's a it's a potential superpower
India is nowhere close to being a
superpower right now let's not delude
ourselves lots of Indians keep asking me
every single day about when will India
become a superpowers India reach there
or not no we are nowhere near being a
superpower but we are now a great power
we are now of major power we are one of
the three or four major powers in the
world
but we are nowhere close to being a
superpower we could be a superpower in
the next 20 to 50 years it's certainly
possible it's actually probable if
things continue the way that they're
continuing
and that's why India is a long-term
adversity for the U.S and that's why
they would take steps now to ensure that
India never reaches that stage of of
being a possible threat or adversity or
competitor to the U.S economically
militarily or any which way whatsoever
they don't want that to happen they want
India to remain this mentally colonized
peace I mean piece of geography with
with people who who are content in
mediocrity and who think everything is
great and who think that everything any
progress is bad that's what they would
like India to be like so yeah yeah so um
so they would certainly
use every tool in the tool book and they
have a very very extensive tool book
they've used all kinds of tools in the
past in the past 100 years more or less
of the dominant 70 years of the
dominance ever since they became the top
dog in the world after 1945 1943 1944
onwards yes
so they have a lot of experience in
managing Nations and managing uh
aspiring powers and how to ensure that
they don't become real powers and one of
the ways is to embroil that nation in
war and there is a ready-made
adversary for India the British created
the British partitioned India for this
reason it had the partition of India had
geopolitical uh itself the geopolitical
objectives of the UK and the US
that is something I can go into at
another point in time so that's why
India was partitioned right and that's
why this this hostile neighbors
neighboring state was created now on
both sides of India now we were able to
deal with one power one side of it which
is more or less
uh less hostile to India right but
Pakistan Still Remains Pakistan is still
independent right now yes Pakistan
temporarily is independent Pakistan
temporarily is is a result of the U.S
and they can use Pakistan in a variety
of ways to to counterbalance India and
to keep India off balance and one of the
ways of doing that
is by enrolling India India in a war
with Pakistan which could possibly
destroy Pakistan but that's okay that's
okay that's a throw of the dice it's a
chess move right when you've got so many
pieces to play with on the chessboard
you can afford to sacrifice one or two
so um and of course they would want to
use Pakistan as long as possible against
India to keep India off balance so it is
possible that uh we may see some hostile
action from from from Pakistan in the
future in the upcoming future it's
possible whether it is in the form of a
resumption of terrorist activities they
could try doing that they could try uh
you know cross-border terrorism they
could try cross-border of infiltration
of drugs and all that into India to to
destabilize the Border regions of India
uh there are lots of tools the disposal
they can use drones for that I think if
the the Indian authorities are
intercepting Pakistani drones almost on
a daily basis which which container
which which carry this payload of drugs
or whatever it is that's already
happening uh terrorism hasn't resumed if
they try that they could
face a significant backlash from India
and and you know an asymmetric backlash
most likely but yes these are various
tools in the toolkit and they could be
used at whatever time uh they see as
appropriate so it is certainly now I
think now
I think now it seems that in
india-pakistan war in the future is more
likely than an India China war that's
how it looks to me right now let's keep
an eye on this things are changing very
fast but now one thing that is for sure
is that Pakistan is now firmly back in
the U.S Camp the Chinese have lost all
control of Pakistan yes and the
pakistanis will now do whatever their
American Masters tell them
so that's where we are
okay two questions one is by krishiv and
one is by Daniel
what would provoke a country to use
nukes nuclear weapons according to you
and the other question is in the event
of a nuclear exchange between India and
the temperature Pakistan and India and
the People's Republic of China how will
the Indian nuclear Doctrine perceive the
supposed response from India towards
Pakistan visaway PRC surely India must
Reserve an extinction level response for
Pakistan but how will India respond to a
Chinese nuclear provocation assuming
India's nuke threshold is breached does
our nuclear doctrines response change
from Nation to nation and is it about
time for us to change our no First
Strike policy all right good questions
so the first question is about nuclear
red lines what would provoke a country
to use nukes according to you well every
nation has its own perception of its red
lines the Russians are some Nations have
this no first use policy that there will
never be the first nation to use nuclear
weapons but they will use nuclear
weapons in retaliation to a first strike
by another Nation some Nations have do
not have a no first news policy which
means that they reserve the right to
renew to use nuclear weapons first now
most Nations declare this now these
Declarations of intent do we need to
take them seriously I mean things change
and it's let's say you have a policy of
no first use is that stated policy more
important than your National interest
let's say circumstances change and you
are in a position when you're very know
that your nation is on the brink of
annihilation for whatever reason let's
say hypothetically right in that case
does it not make does it not make sense
to do a first strike in order to save
your nation from being annihilated even
if the adversary has not used nuclear
weapons that is a question that has to
be addressed and how do you address the
question you ask yourself what is more
important is the natural interest more
important is the survival of the nation
more important or is my stated policy
more important it's very clear that your
National interest always has to be
Paramount whatever statements and
pronouncements you have made in the past
are words words can be changed words you
can go back on your words what's what's
wrong with that right that's how it goes
in geopolitics so uh if we have India
obviously we know has a stated no first
use policy well we can take that policy
with a couple of grains of salt
and every nation has its own perception
of red lines for instance Russia has um
all of its territory falls under the
nuclear umbrella so whatever territory
is part of Russia if there is a
possibility of the territory being
overrun by a hostile Force
then the Russia reserves to use the
right to use nuclear weapons in defense
of the territory to safeguard the
territorial Integrity of Russia so that
is the clear red line that Russia has uh
when it comes to Israel now we know that
Israel is a nuclear weapons power they I
don't know what number of nukes they
have but they have a significant uh
non-itrivial number of nuclear weapons
they have a reasonably good stockpile of
nuclear weapons I think the number
that's thrown around by the so-called
experts is between 70 and 120 or
whatever 17 180 whatever the number is
they have a decent number of nuclear
weapons and the objective they call it
the Samson option the Samson
s-a-m-s-o-n Samson option that's what
Israel calls its nuclear uh stockpile so
the the objective of the nuclear stock
price stockpile is very clear it's it's
that in the case Israel is facing
imminent destruction they will
annihilate all their neighbors whoever
is is up against them in this uh Samsung
option Maybe destroy Israel as well but
we will not let anybody survive this
sort of thing
so that is the Samsung option it is
assured destruction of its neighbors of
of its enemies not neighbors not
necessarily neighbors but whoever is
hostile to Israel let's say there is a
war between Israel and whatever other
hostile neighbor or nation and if that
nation is on the brink of overrunning
and destroying Israel
then Israel deserves the right to
annihilate the nation totally right and
it may also result in the annihilation
of Israel but that's fine so we will not
let you succeed no matter what the cost
so that is the nuclear red line that
Israel has it is obviously uh something
that you will be you will be used only
as a last resort so every nation has
different perceptions of red lines now
when it comes to India like I said we
have the stated no first use policy so
let's say we get embroiled in a nuclear
exchange let's say with Pakistan
so I think Visa I think
the nuclear policy or doctrine will
differ from Nation to know when it comes
to conflicts with various Nations I'm
sure that India's policy or doctrine
Visa with China will most likely be
different from India's policy or
doctrine Pakistan
Pakistan is a different case China has a
different case and both will be
approached in a different way that's
that has that is most likely the case so
let's say India gets involved in nuclear
scene with Pakistan and the Pakistan is
the first to launch a nuclear missile or
whatever it is right
they are the first to bridge the nuclear
threshold
in that case I think it's very clear
that the Indian response will be
disproportionate it will be an
extinction level response if if Pakistan
dares to use even a single nuke Pakistan
will no longer exist within the next
half an hour there is a guarantee not
next half an hour next 10 minutes most
likely yeah so I I see these are all
hypotheticals we never ever want to see
nuclear weapons being used being used
again ever against human beings against
civilians it should never ever happen
this is not something that you can it's
not a joke it's not something that's
this is a very serious matter so we
never ever want this to happen but in
the hypothetical scenario that it
happens India will most likely
uh have a disproportionate extinction
level response towards Pakistan if the
pakistanis breached the nuclear
threshold Pakistan will be erased from
the map of the world that's that's very
clear Pakistan will cease to exist as an
as a nation
we hope and pray it never happens we we
never want this to happen I have
absolutely nothing against my uh against
the people of Pakistan I have nothing
against them it's the nation that's a
terrorist State and that has to be dealt
with in the right way when the time is
right so that's about Pakistan Visa with
China well the Chinese aren't crazy
the Chinese uh they have spent
they have expended a huge amount of
energy and hard work and labor and money
in building up the nation to whatever
stage it has reached China is nearly a
middle in combination now it has
developed so much so much since the
1970s and 1980s are they crazy would
they be crazy to to
willingly risk all of that in a nuclear
extinct with India
because it's almost impossible to defend
every resource that you have and it's
almost impossible to defend every city
that you have yeah and even the
anti-ballistic missile technology isn't
foolproof especially when you have marvs
and mirv Technology maneuvering vehicles
and you know multiple independent
re-entry Vehicles so single missile can
carry let's say 10 warheads and these
Warheads they go in different directions
and they maneuver while going down it's
almost impossible to intercept that so
if the Chinese cross the nuclear
threshold they are guaranteed to be met
with an Indian retaliation nuclear
retaliation and this could come from any
part of India or even from the ocean
because we now have nuclear submarines
which are on patrol yeah we will soon
have multiple nuclear submarines the
Chinese are not crazy they will not I
mean only a Madman would what even
envisage crossing the nuclear threshold
with a nation like India so I think if
let's say hypothetically the Chinese do
cross the nuclear threshold India will
obviously response respond to that and
I am sure India already
see every nation has a set of targets
let's say you are China you have a set
of ready-made targets that you know you
want to Target in case of a nuclear
exchange with India or with Russia over
the US oh Russia is very much in the
crosshairs right the Russians they will
also have
this predefined set of targets let's say
I get into a nuclear exchange with the
U.S which targets will it take out it's
like automatically programmed just press
a button and the first strike happens
the First Response happens and so on so
these are all predetermined targets
these are all determined but you keep on
tracking them and see how it goes so
that's how it goes so in case there is a
nuclear reaction between India and
Pakistan Pakistan will cease to exist
India will take some damage obviously
but Pakistan will be annihilated when it
comes to Indian China if the Chinese do
this this Chinese will face a
significant losses and they will lose a
lot of what they've built over the past
30 40 years that's that's guaranteed so
it is
like mutually assured destruction when
it comes to India and China India can
certainly come out on top vis-a-vis a
hypothetical nucleation with Pakistan
before they can do too much damage we
can wipe them off the map these are with
China it's it's a more complicated China
is a very large country and most of
their uh population centers and large
cities are far from India let's let's
take a look at the map shall we
so if we look at the Chinese map
the map of China uh most of the the
entire Heartland of China the population
centers are in the east of China and
what the regions that are contiguous
with India and close to India which is a
Tibet and xinjiang these are mostly
empty very little population it's only
in the green parts of the map over here
the durable population Center
significant population centers and in
this industrial centers like Wuhan
Chengdu Chongqing Guangzhou uh Hong Kong
Shanghai Beijing and so on so forth
right these are all far from India but
they are very much Within Reach of
India's nuclear missiles so so that's
the scenario the Chinese and Indians
both know that if this ever happens it
is essentially mutually a short
destruction the the the the Chinese will
lose
a lot of what they've built over the
past 30 40 years and India will also
you never also stand to lose a lot it's
major cities and all that we never ever
want this to happen so when it comes to
nuclear exchanges and all the theory
behind it every nation is taken as a
when you are when when you're India you
approach every Potential Threat
differently you will have a different
response tailor-made for each nation in
case this ever happens and we never want
this to happen so yeah that's how it
goes obviously I am
I am talking from the perspective of
logic the logic of strategy I am not
privy to India's nuclear Doctrine actual
nuclear plants or any such thing right I
am simply giving you a logical
assessment of how I see it from the
using the logic of strategy in
geopolitics NGO strategy and geography
okay Arya says uh brics countries are
working on developing a brics currency
and the brics central bank is going to
be situated in gift City India what will
be its impact on on the world and on
India well when it comes to creating
your own currency when it first of all
every nation has its own currency that's
fine but when you come together as a
group of Nations and you create your own
currency
that's essentially a challenge to the
existing hegemony of the US dollar now
the the reason one of the major Central
reasons why the US is the superpower is
because the U.S dollar the U.S currency
is the world's Reserve currency most of
the World's Trade Etc is all done in in
U.S dollars it's called The Petroleum
dollar for reason most of the evolves
trade in petroleum was also until very
recently even now it's all mostly all
done in you in US dollars so the US
controls the world's Reserve currency
they can print as much as of it as they
want they can manipulate exchange rates
they can do whatever they want with it
and they can
affect the entire world by doing that so
if you have a new currency that comes up
and lots of Nations decide agree to use
that currency instead of the US dollar
that's a major challenge to the US and
you don't do these things lightly these
are dangerous things to do because it
will invite a response a retaliation
from the U.S you know
and this sort of this is Warfare
through a different means and it can
invite a different kind of response
through other means so even through
kinetic means possibly so uh it's it's
nice I I'm not sure if this has been
announced maybe there are plans maybe
there's speculation about this happening
in the future but it will have to be
approached very very cautiously very
delicately because this represents a
major challenge to the U.S hegemony on
the world and you don't challenge the
existing hegemund the existing
superpower lightly you have to be very
careful when you do that
but yes uh there are these things in
motion plans in motion I'm thinking I'm
sure there are secret talks being being
conducted secret plans been been drawn
out and all that already there are
nations that are trading in in
currencies other than the US dollar we
have the rupee Ruble trade which is
happening between India and Russia uh
there is the the
Euro Yuan trade also happening and in a
real
U1 trade also when it comes to China and
the UAE or China and some Gulf Nations
and so on so there are many nations that
are experimenting with these alternative
payment mechanisms and if this gains a
lot of currency then it could kind of
slowly but steadily erode away at the
supremacy and Primacy of the US dollar
and that is something the U.S will not
tolerate
uh but yeah we are they in a position
they are still the major power in the
world they can still do more or less
what they want at any part of the world
they still have the ability so that's
why this has to be approached very
carefully but yes in the long run if
there's a group of Nations that wants to
create a new world order maybe create a
bifurcation of the existing world order
then they will have to de-dollarize
their industry their economies yeah D
dollarization that's a very dangerous
word
and yeah one of the ways of doing it is
is to create a common currency let's say
a brics currency now bricks could expand
you could have a bricks plus a bricks
plus plus south of South Africa the
South African president has uh revealed
or claimed
revealed that that Saudi Arabia wants to
become a part of brics was to become a
brics member Iran wants to become a
member of brics and there are various
other nations in in Latin America and
other places who would possibly want to
become members of brics
so when you have a coalition of Nations
The Core Power in that Coalition in the
grouping the grouping is typically
controlled by the nation that has the
most power and right now it's China but
China's power is not that great nowadays
it's China is a little subdued these
days because of various setbacks it has
faced very very strong setbacks it has
faced in the past two years two to three
years yes so the Chinese are a little
more subdued now so the core grouping in
brics is the Ric grouping Russia India
China Russia is under under Fire from
from the west from NATO from the U.S
India is is playing a balancing act
China is now taking it easy not being
very aggressive these days uh and yet if
these nations find a way to come
together through their common interests
through their share interests and bring
more Nations together they could be able
to create a significant grouping of
Nations and then if they issue their own
currency and agree to trade in that
currency only then that could represent
a significant challenge to the Supremacy
and hegemony of the U.S dollar and the
US itself right so that could be we are
obviously already seeing this emerging
bifurcation of the world order there is
the rules the so-called rules-based
world order that the U.S has run for the
past 70 years which is more or less the
U.S whims-based world order whatever
they decide is the rule and that could
change next week or whatever but yeah
that's how it's been so they have
controlled the entire global economy
through the US dollar see ever since
1940 344 which was the year the Bretton
Woods agreement happened I think it was
one year before the end of the of the
second world war and ever since then
there they have controlled the global
economy and the US dollar has reigned
Supreme even after the the petroleum
crisis in the 1970s was it also yeah
1970s right and so on that's when it
became the petrol right it de-linked
itself from gold but now if you have a
common brics currency and lots of
Nations join brics and maybe if you can
Peg the brics currency to the price of
gold or something another that could
make this currency a very valuable and
and
um
something very lucrative somebody is
something that people would want to have
yeah so yeah it could happen but it has
to be done
judiciously delicately
and with a lot of caution because it
will obviously invite a significant
response from the nation that stands the
most to lose from such a thing happening
which is the U.S and you don't want to
be
very overtly on the bad side of the U.S
right I think it would be great if there
are multiple currencies in the world
that are strong uh right now it's only
one currency I mean you have other
currencies that have a high value the UK
pound is a high value the Euro but these
are all proxies for the US dollar these
nations are not controlled by the U.S so
they don't represent any real challenge
to the U.S the Yen was also one of these
so all the yuan is the one Challenger
right now
to the US dollar the ruble also is doing
very well because they have pegged the
ruble to the price of gold and so on so
if you create a brics currency and maybe
Peg that to the price of gold that could
be a significant Challenger it could
happen but yeah we are still in in very
early stages very preliminary stages if
this happens and if the brick central
bank is in India then that could
represent the challenge to to the U.S
from India's side so yeah we are seeing
a very rapid
reshaping of the world order and it's
not nearly close done it's gonna it's
gonna go on and things are gonna shake
be shaken up a lot the whole entire
world order is going to be shaken up a
lot we are most likely just in the
beginning phases of that so yeah things
are not gonna get much more interesting
and much more intense as the years go by
in the 2020s months go by five years
months
much
okay summer says Dr s Jai Shankar is
going to visit Russia on the 8th of
November citing an escalation of the
Ukraine conflict can India become a sort
of a mediator and ensure that no nuclear
weapons of any sort are used by both the
sides your thoughts about this important
upcoming visit considering Russia was to
hold a bilateral Summit with India this
year
good question here so it's been
announced that uh our foreign minister
Dr Jay Shankar will be visiting Russia
on November 8th uh I'm not sure what
they have cited it doesn't matter what
they've cited it's it's uh
it's an important development now I'm
sure you know that India and Russia have
this agreement that every year once a
year there will be a bilateral Summit
between the leaders of the two Nations
and this is a tradition that's been
going on for several years uh last year
because of the pandemic uh Mr Putin did
come to India it was a very hurried
visit but he made sure that he comes in
December he came in December he it was a
very rapid flying visit he was in India
only for five hours his team arrived
before him and then he came to India he
met the Prime Minister straight from the
airport to the prime minister's house
residents and they had their meeting the
summit five hours and then he went back
and this is something that happened in
the Prelude to the Ukraine conflict
right so last year Mr Putin ensured that
he did keep the commitment and he came
to India now this year we don't know
what's going to happen is the summit
going to happen or not this this year
it's Mr modi's turn to go and visit
Moscow now he will obviously be under
pressure from the United States and the
west and NATO do not do this yeah if
they so if the the summit doesn't happen
this year then the West could interpret
that or spin that as some kind of win on
their side against Russia and so on so
as of now we don't know if a summit is
going to happen this year or not we're
already in deep into October now the
almost November right so two months ago
for the end of the year and the summit
hasn't happened it's not been announced
so yeah so we don't quite know yet
whether this will happen and whether Mr
Modi will make the trip to Moscow and
and uh hold the summit with Mr Putin of
course you can also hold a virtual
Summit but that's not quite the same
thing right that has a that doesn't have
the same well the same Optics and same
same significance as two leaders meeting
and hugging and you know all that so uh
so right now what we know is Dr Jai
Shankar is going to visit Moscow on
November 8 he's going to meet his
counterpart uh Mr lavrov and maybe some
other important Russian leaders we don't
know if you'll meet Mr Putin it doesn't
matter maybe maybe not but he's going
there he's a very he's India's top
diplomat so um the question now is a
will India or can India become a
mediator between the two sides in the
conflict and ensure that no significant
escalation happens and uh no nuclear
weapons obviously are used on either
side I think India is in the prime
position for doing this if there is any
Nation right now that is equally let's
say friendly there is no friendship as
we know in geopolitics but let's just
use the term loosely if there is one
nation right now if there is a major
power in the world right now that is
equally friendly and comfortable with
both sides it's India there is no other
nation that has the stature of India
right now that can talk equally well
with with with the same amount of warmth
and curtsy and all that
and Trust as India
so when it comes to India we can talk to
the Russians with a great amount of
warmth and there's a great amount of uh
uh Trust on both sides when it comes to
India and the West the same amount of
trust may not be there but there is a
great amount of comfort level we have
been dealing with the West for a very
long time yes for the past 30 or so
years and Mr Modi has made lots of
visits there he's very comfortable very
very familiar with how things work there
our diplomats have had this
long-standing understanding and and
contacts with the West so India is in in
India is right now playing this
Balancing Act it is
pursuing an independent foreign policy
it's buying all from the west from from
Russia from Russia it's also engaging
with the West in a multitude of ways so
India is in pole position to play the
role of a diplomatic mediator and in
short maybe as as a means of
communication between the two sides is a
mediator yeah and ensure that tensions
don't go beyond boiling point and things
don't escalate too much
India has consistently through various
officials through various leaders
whether it is Mr rajnath Singh whether
it is Dr jashankar or whether it is
Prime Minister Modi himself India has
repeatedly said this the same refrain
that this is not the time for war and
these conflicts need to be resolved
through diplomacy not Warfare and all
that
while pursuing India's own National
interest in the whole matter so I think
India is in a very good position and
India may possibly be the only nation
that can play this role right now yeah
so things are going to change now this
winter I think uh there's gonna be
energy crisis food crisis all that in
Europe I hope it doesn't make the people
of Europe suffer too much I hope not I
suffering is never good but yeah we can
see it happening
and maybe the two sides Russia and NATO
will get entrenched in their positions
possibly in Ukraine your Russia's next a
quarter or so of Ukraine or maybe a
fifth of Ukraine it will enrich its
positions there and and consolidate it
its hold on those regions you could see
offensives you may not and I certainly
hope there is no crossing of the nuclear
threshold there has been too much talk
of this too much irresponsible talk of
crossing the nuclear threshold how a
limited nuclear war could be good for
climate change for the environment in
global warming and there's been this
talk of dirty bombs you know and so on
these are very dangerous things to talk
about in the west media seems to be
trying to normalize and trivialize this
thing and now the Russians have made
this claim this allegation that the the
NATO side Ukraine or whatever is is
planning to use a dirty bomb in a fall
flag attack so these are very dangerous
times we're living through and we do not
want to see a crossing of the nuclear
threshold on whatever side
it's it's
not something you ever want to see so I
think India is is in pole position for
playing a mediator's role you know a
nation that's trusted on both sides a
nation that has very good relationships
on both sides
and a nation that does desire peace we
do not want to see things escalate it's
not good for India it's not good for
Europe it's not good for anybody in the
world we do not want an escalation of
this conflict
it could it could impact the economy
worldwide it could create a terrible
fuel crisis food crisis especially in
the so-called Global South especially in
the poor nations in Africa it could even
affect India up to some extent or to a
large extent we do not want these things
to happen
so it is in our interest and it is in
the world's interest that the Ukraine
conflict does not escalate Beyond
certain lines it should not happen and I
think it is it is
possibly going to be India's role to
play
um
uh to play the mediator's roles in this
conflict so yes this could be why this
could be one of the reasons why Dr
jajankar is visiting Moscow maybe he's a
very active and very busy person
um he's been traveling non-stop in
meeting with various of various
counterparts non-stop ever since the
conflict started I'm not sure how much
sleep is getting but he is very active
very busy and he's doing a stellar job
at this so maybe he'll have to take on
an additional responsibility perhaps to
as that of a mediator between both sides
as a bridge to communicate with both
sides while also taking care of the
international interest in Indian
diplomacy so yes yeah that could be
happening that that's something that is
certainly on the cards so we're not
quite sure what the agenda is what is
the stated agenda if there is any of
this upcoming visit but yes he will
certainly discuss the security situation
the energy situation India Russia uh
defense cooperation ties and maybe the
possibility of an upcoming Summit
between the two leaders in Moscow or
somewhere else in Russia this year so
there's going to be a number of things
to discuss
and let's see what is the outcome of
that but it's certainly a very important
visit in the context of how things are
going right now so yeah I think I'm sure
the world will be watching this this
visit and we'll be watching with
different expectations but let's see how
it goes yeah
okay other says
you mentioned in previous sessions that
the US has mostly contained China in its
quest to become another superpower does
that mean that it no longer needs India
as a counterweight to China
will this intensify breaking India
activities toward unprecedented level
how can we be prepared
yes so I have indeed mentioned
multiple times that I do not see China
um yeah the U.S does seem to have
contained China to a certain extent
China does not seem to be on track
anymore to become a superpower and why
do I say this it's because the the the
vehicle that the Chinese government that
the Chinese Communist Party wanted to
use for to to to
as the vehicle for China's rise to super
power status that vehicle was the
built-in Road initiative the Bri the one
belt one road and the the uh Maritime
silk route so that's that's like two
things but it had the same purpose right
infrastructure building and connecting
China with with the rest of Eurasia with
Europe mostly yeah so that was the OBO R
thing and one of the its components was
the cpec China Pakistan economic
corridor so that's that was China's
great bid for super power status
construct construction of this massive
amount of infrastructure investment of
hundreds of billions of dollars maybe
trillions of dollars in creating this
infrastructure which would integrate
China's economy with that of Eurasia
and also with Africa and all other
places that produce raw materials
minerals and various real natural
resources and that was supposed to uh
to to
fuel China's rise to super power status
now what's happened in the past since
2019 we know what happened the pandemic
and that brought the entire world's
economy to a grinding halt
in China
seems to have been affected more than
any other Nation even now they have
these uh incredibly harsh lockdowns that
are still going on in China the rest of
the world has moved on from the pandemic
right in India I think it's only the
airlines that that force people to wear
masks for no reason whatsoever
you know you come to the airport without
a mask you mingle with hundreds of
people thousands of people but on board
you have to wear a mask for one hour two
or three years whatever and then you go
back to normal things and while eating
in the in the plane you can it's okay to
not wear a mask it's stupid bureaucratic
nonsense anyhow India is still laboring
under that but apart from that India no
no longer is bothered about the pandemic
the pandemic hopefully is a thing of the
past no one's wearing masks everyone's
vaccinated so it's the thing of the past
in the Indian vaccine as opposed to
other vaccines the Indian vaccine
actually works so India and the rest of
the world more or less has put the
pandemic behind it the Americans are
still insisting that the the the vaccine
has to be the boosted roses have to be
taken every year or so it's like a
vaccine as a service you have software
as a service right they are using this
new concept of vaccine as a service to
keep enriching their their
pharmaceutical Giants apparently
whatever so the rest of the world has
moved on from the pandemic the Chinese
are still reeling under the pandemic
they still have this zero covet policy
there's very harsh lockdowns which are
crippling the Chinese economy it's still
happening now so I wonder why the
Chinese are being forced the Chinese are
not stupid
they will not do this unless they have a
very good reason for doing this
so there's something happening in China
which we don't quite sure what it is and
this pandemic this virus has affected
China more than any other Nation
the Chinese economy is crumbling it's
it's crawling they are not even
revealing the GDP figures anymore that's
how bad it is yeah
so the Chinese economic machine has gone
to a halt the nation has been ravaged by
this virus we have all been blaming the
Chinese Chinese for the virus but look
at who who it has hurt the most and who
is it has it benefited the most look at
it from that perspective the cost
benefit perspective who has it cost the
most and who has the pandemic benefited
the most that is that gives you that
that's very revealing when you when you
do that analysis so the Chinese seem to
have suffered more than any other Nation
as a consequence of the pandemic it has
destroyed the economy not destroyed
entirely the economy is still there the
machine is still there the industrial
machine the economy machine is still
there but the output is very low now the
GDP growth is is very very low it's it's
crawling it's like one person or two
person or something earlier it was like
ten percent Plus for the longest time
under Mr hujin Tao
it's crawling
so the Chinese are no longer in a
position to become a superpower anytime
soon and as a consequence of the Ukraine
conflict they were hoping that the
Western sanctions on Russia would force
Russia to come crawl into China and then
the Chinese would be able to extract all
kinds of lopsided concessions from the
Russians which would essentially turn
Russia into a Chinese visal state that
was the Great Big Hope
that did not happen because India
prevented it from happening India
started buying 50 times more oil than
before from the Russians and that
ensured that the Russians did not have
to go crawling to the Chinese and
begging for help the Russians were able
to preserve their precious strategic
autonomy because India did this the
Russians have been saved by India and
that has
been something the Chinese did not seem
to have expected this was not part of
their calculations so all of their
calculations have
been a Miss
and they have not been able to achieve
the objectives they were hoping for from
hoping for right
so Russia it's a strategic autonomy is
is intact it is obviously Russia has
certainly been battered by the Western
sanctions but they are still able to
stand stand tall
or stand not not on the they're not not
yet on their knees they have been uh
rescued to some extent by the Indians
right so because of this you could
certainly say and and the the Americans
are now engaging in this trade war with
the Chinese they are uh imposing a
variety of sanctions in the Chinese
especially this the the uh sanctions
against the Chinese semiconductor
industry the chip industry lots of
people I saw in the comments are saying
that it's not going to affect China
anymore please please grow up a little
bit do some proper analysis uh it's
going to affect China a lot the Chinese
do have a lot of capabilities a lot of
expertise in making semiconductors but
when it comes to The Cutting Edge
technology they are dependent completely
on the Americans whether it is for for
for for components or whether it is in
terms of expertise human expertise
so the Americans have said that any
American citizen who works in the
Chinese chip industry in China stands to
lose their American citizenship unless
there is an immediately can go back to
the U.S so that has overnight taken out
all the expertise
the cutting-edge expertise of the
Chinese needed yeah and uh the Chinese
are no longer going to receive any
components from the U.S the cutting-edge
components the need for The Cutting Edge
technology the research and development
and all that so yes they have some
expertise and they're going to keep on
doing that but
the future growth of the industry the
semiconductor industry the chip industry
is is in great Jeopardy right now in
China and they they don't quite know
what to do yes they could retaliate
uh in a variety of ways there could be a
reciprocal trade War the Chinese control
what 70 80 90 whatever it is of the
world's Rare Earth rare earth metals yes
minerals so they could impose some kind
of an embargo in the U.S from from that
perspective so that could make things
really ugly and we could all suffer as a
consequence of that you want to buy your
laptops mobiles tablets whatever it is
buy it now you may have you may run into
a shortage in the upcoming months if
this escalates so so the Chinese are
more or less contained now they are
still in independent nation they still
have an independent foreign policy they
still have a massive Navy they are still
trying to upgrade their military and and
bolster the military muscle
but the Mojo is gone the Mojo is gone
the economic growth has flattened the
Chinese population is aging so all of
this is happening
and if you look at it from a big picture
perspective from from a you know 10
kilometer perspective it is clear that
the Chinese economic growth has stalled
and China is no longer on track to
become a genuine superpower their great
hope and aspiration was to replace and
displace the us as the world's sole
superpower by around 2015. that doesn't
seem to be anywhere near happening now
right so this tells you that there's
only one superpower now in the world as
of now the US and there are three great
Powers India Russia China
in this extremely uncomfortable Tango
together India Russia China Russia
doesn't trust China India doesn't trust
China China trusts neither and yet we
are somehow together in bricks so that's
where we are right so as as the second
see there have been there have been two
cold Wars the first cold war was in the
1900s in the 20th century and now we
were in the middle of the second Cold
War which was between America the US and
China
and the U.S China relationship or or or
adversary relationship relationship was
in parallel with the India China with
the India China adversarial relationship
so the U.S needed India as a
counterweight to China
as china Rose in the Americans needed
India to rise as well
but now that China is no longer Rising
it appears that India may not have so
much use from the U.S perspective which
is why they are now turning their focus
back on Pakistan
as a counterweight to India and as a
counterweight to China as well possibly
you could see all kinds of weird stuff
happening in
in xinjiang
you could see an escalation of terrorist
activities in xinjiang
you know the xinjiang region is is
claimed by The Eagles as their Homeland
and they they have this Independence
Movement they say that the Chinese are
persecuting them and the West the
Western Nations claim that there is a
Chinese persecution and genocide of the
egos happening in xinjiang
and you could see
cross-border terrorism emanating from
from Pakistan into xinjiang
that so that sort of thing would happen
so the so Pakistan right now has a great
amount of utility for the U.S it is
useful against India it's also useful
against China so right now
the way things have gone the way things
have been engineered somehow or the
other in the last two three years
China's rise has stalled and as a
consequence of that the U.S does not
need India that much anymore as a
counterweight to China
right as a consequence you could see the
Americans using Pakistan to
counterbalance India because they don't
want India to rise and become the next
China and you could see various breaking
India activities also Rising we know
what these are there are various
aspiring zelenskies within India various
politicians of various use all mediocre
people you know
and they they there are multiple
aspiring zelenskis who are currently
auditioning for the role of the top
zelinski in India
and these are all funded by the West if
you look at if you follow the money
where the see you cannot have a
political movement without money please
understand this
you may be the greatest person in the
world with the most amount of leadership
qualities in the world but unless you
know how to organize a movement organize
a party from the Grassroots up a proper
leadership hierarchy no organization can
work without a proper hierarchy
it's called organization every in every
political party in every political
movement there are people who specialize
in organization
Sardar Patel was one of those he was Mr
Gandhi's go to man for organizing and
disciplining the congress party
Mr Mohandas Gandhi would not have been
able to achieve anything was it not for
the unquestioning obedience
of Mr Patel Mr Patel was Mr Gandhi's
enforcer in the congress party he wasn't
part of organization and discipline so
in any political movement
in any political party you need proper
organization well-oiled organization and
discipline and this is impossible to
achieve without large infusions of money
because you need to organize things you
need infrastructure you need Vehicles
you need to pay people
at the Grassroots level people will not
work for you unless you pay them
they may have the same agenda as you
they may have the same ideology as you
but unless you pay them they will not be
in a position to work for you and serve
you
this is how power Works my dear friends
power
power and money all over again isn't it
so money and power
so so you need all that
once you have a proper control over the
system then it's yours but when you are
building it up you need infusions of
money and political parties get money
from various quarters from various
sources and when you have aspiring
zelinski you want to create their own
artificial movements they need money for
that and expertise and this expertise
comes from outside much of it comes from
outside I'm assuming I'm not naming
zelinsky is a hypothetical term I'm
using I'm not pointing fingers at any
individual person or politician in India
please understand that I'm just saying
there are various aspiring zelenskies
and for them to sustain their movements
they need infusions of cash and money
from outside
so all of that is the the the the West
has perfected this
over a very long period of time
they have run so many different client
states in various parts of the world in
various African nations they've propped
up lots of dictators they know how it's
done they're proper property of
dictators in the Middle East Saddam
Hussein was once their guy there have
been many more yeah there are right now
many many politicians in various parts
of the world who are still on the
payroll of the West
look at the the rwanda's president
Africa's favorite dictator who has been
in power for more than 20 years more or
less yeah and there are many other
examples so the West knows how to run
the show and to and how to run these
fake Grassroots movements into prop up
zelen's keys in various parts of the
world and yes this this is already
happening in India it's been happening
for the longest time actually in India
in a variety of ways so yes you could
see an intensification of these what are
termed what what we term as breaking
India activities
sub-national diplomacy listen once again
I am not pointing fingers at any
politician I don't know who has said
what and who has not said what but
typically if any politician
within India
talks about subnational diplomacy I
would I would
I would bet that it's possible it is it
it is a possibility to some extent that
there may be some funding coming in for
for that political movement from maybe
somewhere else of the country
yeah sub National diplomacy is a very
big two tool in the toolkit
and this is all all about creating
fissures and fragments fragmentation and
divisions within a nation and exploiting
those to destabilize the nation and to
corrupt it and to co-opt it
and to hijack it from within
so these things will happen and that
that's the main reason why
that's the main reason why India has
been hampered for the longest time ever
since 1947 India has had these
various amounts of foreign influence
from various quarters within the country
May sometimes at very high levels in the
government I'm not saying what what up
to what level is gone but yes it's it's
been known it's been revealed that
various people have been on the payrolls
of various foreign agencies
so this would be something that could
intensify in the coming days because
India is no longer that important even
when India was important for the U.S
this was still happening
it could happen even more now it's
possibility certainly possible
okay web of says the US is offering
technology transfer of f414 engine for
the advanced medium combat aircraft that
India is developing
it's also offering local Manufacturing
in India of this jet engine uh
Rolls-Royce which is a British company
is offering its ej200 engine with 130
kilo newtons of trust of thrust and
Safra is considered a weak Contender
because of its low thrust engine what's
your choice the US is using Pratt and
Whitney engine for F-35 and F22 so the
engines that are being offered to India
whether it's by the us or Rolls-Royce
are not the latest most Cutting Edge
engines these are engines that were
conceived and developed in the 1970s and
80s mostly this is not new technology
they're offering us essentially kind of
two generations behind us technology
kind of thing and I'm not sure to what
extent the technology transfer will be
done yeah
because there are certain components in
engines that uh require a great deal of
technical expertise for instance if you
have a commercial jet jetliner let's say
you travel in in across India there are
various jet planes you know Airbus
engines and Airbus planes or Boeing
planes or whatever it is these planes
use your commercial turbojet engines I'm
not sure what the engine is called
in these commercial
airplane engines the temperature inside
reaches nearly 2000 degree Celsius
that is above the melting point point of
most metals that we use whether it is
aluminum or copper or zinc or or
I'm not sure what titanium but certainly
iron and all that
so in order to build an engine to
construct an engine that can whose
internal components which are very
delicate actually
whose internal components can withstand
that that incredible amount of
temperature and the pressure it takes
the knowledge of of
you know exotic materials special
materials special kinds of coating and
special Alloys of metals sometimes you
you have to build an entire blade of a
jet engine from a single Crystal of
metal and so on so this is extremely
Advanced Cutting Edge technology
and they may give you the technology of
everything else but they may not give
you the technology for this in which
case you will have to keep on depending
on them for spare parts every time your
engine has has operated for a certain
number of hours you need to change
certain components in order to maintain
the reliability of the engine and ensure
that the thing goes wrong so for that
you will be apparently dependent on them
for spares so
even in these engines that are being
offered to us whether it's from the US
or the UK or France I am not sure if
there's gonna be a real genuine 100
transfer of Technology
so that's the current run that's a
dilemma that India is currently
wrestling with we do have this amca
program we have we have another t e b t
e twin engine deck based fighter fighter
jet program which is for future uh which
is a future uh
uh Naval fighter plane that we will be
having and obviously we have the AMC
program the advanced medium combat
aircraft the fifth generation fighter
plane that we are developing none of
these fighter planes will can operate
without a reliable jet engine and you
need a jet engine with a certain amount
of thrust
the current uh so we have India has been
developing the kaveri engine for a very
very long time so the 1980s or something
I think it's right now able to produce I
don't know 70 or 80 kilo newtons of
thrust which is not very bad but it is
kind of underpowered
so when you have a single engine Jet
Plane like the pages I think we are
relying on one of these uh
one of these f414 or 404 engines from
from from the US right uh I'm not sure
what is the the amount of thrust it's
producing must be in excess of 100 kilo
newtons for sure because if you're if
you only have one jet engine for for a
plane it needs to be significantly uh
it needs to produce a significant amount
of thrust above a certain limit
so it's clear the cauvery jet engine is
not currently up to the mark for
powering the uh
the pages fighter blade unless you put
two coverage editors when in which case
it would be fine but we then you you
will have to completely reconfigure the
aircraft which takes years you know
so uh the kaveri engine can be used on
certain drones on certain autonomous you
know remote controlled vehicles and so
on so it does have its utility it can be
reconfigured repurposed for various uh
cruise missiles perhaps and there's a
lot you can do with the cover engine but
it needs to go to the next level it
needs to cross the 100 kilo Newton
thrust threshold then hopefully we
should be I don't know what's what the
status is it's obviously something
that's uh kept under wraps and we don't
quite know what the status is we know
that the the French companies are from
has been uh involved in some aspects of
the kaveri engines development or maybe
some other engines development
um and I'm not sure if the technology
transfer has been done 100 entirely so
yeah that that is the major Achilles
heel when it comes to Indian
fighter plane development a reliable
indigenous engine once we cross that
threshold we are home free we are
independent more or less because now we
know how to design a good quality
fighter plane we have done we have we
have gone through a mountain of lava
more or less we have gone through every
single bad experience we can go through
but we now have a reliable world-class
4th generation fighter plane that they
just fight a plane in its various
iterations
it's going to be the uh framework for
creating the next generation of fighter
planes the the amca the te
dbf or whatever it is yeah and maybe
some other fighter planes in the future
as well so now we know how to do it now
it's easy
it's it's much easier not easy but it's
much easier to use that as the framework
for developing the next generation of
fighter planes to design that and to
test it out it will not take that much
time as it took for the pages fighter
plane in the next five six years you
will have a flying amca the only
question is what engine will use will we
be still dependent on foreign engines
whether it's American engines or or UK
Rolls-Royce engines or French engines
engines we could even turn to Russia for
engines but even then we will be
dependent on the Russians we don't want
that that's that is a critical
dependence that that but essentially uh
puts you at somebody else's Mercy
so India needs to develop design and
construct its own indigenous jet engine
that is that produces sufficient thrust
so that is something that is critical to
National interest
and uh so right now what we would have
to do is maybe acquire one of these jet
engines as an interim measure
but um the entire focus at the gtre gas
turbine research establishment in
Bengaluru has to be on somehow or the
other at any cost cost
ensuring that the coverage attention or
whatever jet engine they are working on
gas turbine engine
does the job we needed to do so we need
to develop our own engine
in the interim in in the interim we may
have to acquire one of these engines and
maybe if one of these nations cooperates
and at the right price they may if they
actually transfer the full technology
that would be great in that case we
don't have to reinvent the wheel so when
it comes to National Security it doesn't
matter how you acquire the technology
you buy it you beg for it you borrow it
you steal it doesn't matter acquire it
once you acquire it you can move on to
the next step
buy back borrow still doesn't matter
it's all about the national interest and
it's all fair game so yeah that's where
we are right now and I'm not quite sure
where at what stage we have reached in
the development of an indigenous jet
engine
um
so yeah that's where we are
shrikan says what's your take on NATO
Pilots secretly training Chinese Pilots
one American National Daniel Duggan was
arrested in Australia for the same
reason looks like China secretly has
been secretly funding some Aviation
training academies and a recruiting
Western Pilots to train their pilots for
aircraft carrier missions who will have
more India impact India or the West yeah
I'm not sure about India or the West let
me let's let's address this so what's
happening it's indeed come to light that
various UK I mean British Pilots have
been involved in training
uh Chinese Pilots
uh vis-a-vis their aircraft carrier
missions so these are
British pilots who uh served in the Air
Force and then were released and it
seems like an American National was also
arrested for doing this thing
and when it comes to the UK they have
been appealing to their pilots to come
back and not do this but they don't seem
to have any other measure other other
means that the disposal to let's say
Force these pilots from uh doing this
work so what's really happened
what's really happened is that the UK
especially has this diversity policy in
the armed forces which means that let's
say you you have let's let's say
hypothetically you have 100 Air Force
pilots in the UK so they have this
diversity quotas that at least so and so
percentage must be female let's say
let's say female and at least so and so
person percent of them need to be uh
of other ethnicities not not white not
UK but let's say mixed race or or people
of color like they say or whatever it is
so they have all these artificial quota
requirements like they have in South
African cricket
so
so even if let's say a certain person is
good enough is competent and is
meritorious enough to get into the
program and become pilot that person may
not be allowed to fly for the UK
because of diversity quota requirements
and it looks like many such people have
been released for such reasons
so the question you would ask yourself
is
in what circumstances does a person
betray his or her Nation
it's a psychological thing under what
circumstances is a would a person be
willing to betray his or her Nation
typically
this would happen a person would be
willing to betray their Nation if they
themselves feel like they have been
betrayed by that Nation
right like I deserved something I worked
hard for it I earned it and then my
nation took it away from me and gave it
to somebody less deserving if you have
this feeling inside you and if you have
worked your entire life for something
it's been your dream your goal your
aspiration and you achieved it and it
was taken away from you then you will
certainly have this deep feeling of
betrayal and when you do that to a
person I think it is it opens up the
likelihood that they may actually go
ahead and do something like this like
betraying their nation and cooperating
with a foreign nation that is adversible
to your nation and helping them out
to the detriment of your own National
interest so when you have these
quotas when you do not respect Talent
when you do not respect Merit
that's when you are
undermining your own nation and your own
Society any for Any Nation to prosper
you have to respect Merit
you have to respect Merit you can't have
reservations and quotas that go against
Merit when you do that you are
undermining your own Nation your own
Society you are creating a genuine
feeling of betrayal among your own
people and this is a lesson for India as
well by the way I think we all know that
when you have these quotas
you know when it comes to the armed
forces the armed forces are not an
employment generation scheme this is
something people don't understand in
India or in many other parts of the
world the armed forces have one purpose
it is to safeguard the national interest
the territorial integrity and the
National Security of the nation
the armed forces are not in employment
generation scheme in the armed forces
entry should be open to anybody who
meets the the threshold requirements
right it should be based purely on Merit
you want the best people in your Armed
Forces not People based on various
artificial bureaucratic quotas so that's
what the UK has been doing I think
that's what various Western militaries
have been doing quartiles
and when you have quotas
you will have people who are not quite
deserving who will rise to a certain
position and fill a position and you
will have really well deserving people
who will not get the opportunity because
they have been replied for somebody else
that's what engenders this deep feeling
of resentment and betrayal among the
people and this also happens in
educational institutions when you have
photos in education and all that yeah
and it creates this feeling that I don't
love my country why should I love my
country my country doesn't love me my
country did not give me what I deserve
what I worked for and that's when you
have these betrayals that happen
so you wanna you wanna compromise a
nation you destroy the system of Merit
so that's what's happening here so yeah
an American National has been arrested
in Australia I I also saw the news in
various British Pilots have been
profiting
you know using this as a means to earn
money in China the Chinese will be happy
to give them a very decent salary in
exchange for the work they're doing so
that's what it is a nation that doesn't
treat its people right will be betrayed
many of the people who have who have not
been treated by right by the nation will
still have some self-respect and some
love for the nation that even if my
nation betrayed me I will not be to the
nation but there will always always be
this one person or two person of people
who will be willing to betray the nation
in any society
a certain percentage
let's say out of one lakh people you may
have five people or ten people in any
society who have criminal Tendencies and
who who will be prone to betraying the
nation right this is It's a statistical
certainty that a certain percentage of
the population will have such Tendencies
now so so it's certainly likely that in
a big pool of pilots in the UK If so
many of them or X number of them n
number of them X number of them have
been laid off because of the quota
system it's it's quite likely that if
you approach them if you're Chinese if
you approach these people with us with
the lucrative pay package for a certain
period of time that you work with us for
let's say three years you're gonna give
you this money and you give us your your
transfer expertise was some of them will
be tempted to do it so that's what's
happened and that's happened entirely
because of the policies or policies of
the of the UK in various Western
militaries because now they have various
diversity quotas and gender quotas and
God knows what other quotas I don't know
what it is but this is the root cause of
of this phenomenon that you're
witnessing here
all right
says is India's current geographical
size big enough to attain and retain a
genuine superpower status you I mean I
get these super power questions like
multiple times a day I typically don't
take them but let's let's take this for
a change so is India's current
geographical size big enough to attain
and retain a genuine superpower status
look at the size of India it is enormous
now ask no answer me this question
was the UK's size
geographical size big enough to retain
and attain and retain a genuine
superpower status the UK is a tiny Speck
on the map compared to India and yet it
was able to become a great Empire the
largest Empire that the world has ever
seen until the U.S Empire
so does it have anything to do with
science
the UK is this little tiny little speck
on the map they became a superpower
India is way larger than the UK let's
take another example in 1180 Mongolia
was was a bunch of of ragtag tribes
fighting each other they had no status
in the local region let alone in the
world and yet 40 years later there were
a global superpower
their leader chingis Khan conquered more
land in 20 years
then Roman emperors conquered in 200
years
right so the size of your territory the
size of your geography has nothing to do
with whether you can become a superpower
or not
it's about creating the right system
it's about having the right leadership
you can become a superpower nearly
overnight if you are able to create the
right system a meritocrit meritorious
system a merit A system that respects
Merit and if you have the right
leadership
it can happen nearly overnight if you do
this so please stop thinking in terms of
geography what does it take to become a
superpower
a superpower is a nation that controls
most of the world's resources
resources what are resources we've
spoken about this before raw materials
petroleum products oil gas minerals and
metals agriculture all these things so
how do you control these Resources by
creating the supply chains and by owning
the supply chains you have to create the
infrastructure you have to create
railroads Railways you to create
Maritime trade routes
and you have to ensure that you are able
to defend
all the infrastructure you've created
that's why that's why a superpower needs
a massive military
to safeguard the infrastructure that it
creates that's the real reason why as
super power needs a massive military
right so you need a huge Maritime Force
Merchant Navy and Military Navy you need
an Air Force you need to own all the
supply chains
you need to own the world's Reserve
currency these are the things that it
that it takes to create a genuine
superpower you it doesn't matter how
large or how small you are
the Size Doesn't Matter
it's the ability to create the system
and the ability to defend the system
that matters and that comes from having
the right
system in place in the right leadership
in place
India can become and of course if you
are larger it's easier to become a
superpower so actually India is in a
much better position than the UK was
or any other or Mongolia was you know so
India's geographical size it's is it big
enough it's way bigger than needed to
become a genuine superpower it's all
about creating the right system and
having the right leaders in position
we may be on the path perhaps one hope
so yeah
foreign
want to see how does how do I want to
see India in 2050 choose one a a
technologically advanced Nation or B A
culturally Rich Nation I'm going to take
option C a materially prosperous Nation
what does it mean a nation with a huge
GDP output
if by 2050 India is the world's largest
GDP is India has the world's largest
share of the GDP in excess of what the
U.S and China has
that's what I would like to see because
without being materially prosperous
without being a prosperous or Rich
Nation
without money
you cannot be technological
technologically advanced it's impossible
to be technologically advanced without
having a high amount of prosperity and
once again without having a high amount
of prosperity it is impossible to be
culturally Rich look at all the poor
nations in the world what culture do you
see there they may have had a great
culture in the past but when you are
poor your culture is unimportant there
is no Focus or emphasis on the culture
the only focus is on survival
understand that
so what I would like to see is India
retaining regaining its historical
position as the world's largest economy
that's what I would like to see by 2050.
if we do that then we will certainly be
the most technological imagination and
we will also be a culturally Rich Nation
for both a for both num uh option one
and two to be possible you need to First
be materially prosperous
so by 2050 I would like to see India
become once again
the world's largest economy that's what
I would like to see
a saurabh my friend asks lots of good
questions uh these days we are focusing
more on geopolitics I'm not able to take
so many of these but I appreciate your
questions sorb and here's one of those
so the question is how old is Indian
astronomy are there any rough
estimations of it and how good or bad
was the where ancient Indians in
astronomy as lots of people think
jyotish is pseudoscience the thing they
missed is what they call the science is
jyotish FAL and all
okay the question I'm going to answer is
how old is Indian astronomy
what evidence do we have of Indian
astronomy all our great libraries have
been destroyed and burned so all our
most of our ancient texts have
evaporated
and yet
we have some evidence archaeological
evidence so let's take a look at the
archaeological evidence strangely enough
of Indian astronomy imagine that
archaeological evidence of astronomy
so let's take a look at this uh article
this paper
it's
what is it called
yeah let me put that on the screen so
let's take a look at the oldest possible
advance
evidence of Indian astronomy this is an
article a paper that is available on the
tifr website Tata Institute of
fundamental research Mumbai it's one of
India's Premier physics research
institutes so this is a paper that was
published there by three of their
scientists yes
uh tifr Etc some one of them is from
Potsdam in Germany and so on so forth so
it says the oldest sky chart with
Supernova record and if you go here this
is a photograph of a stone carving from
the Kashmir region in India
uh this Stone carving is dated to uh
it's it's very old
and it it depicts a hunting scene
it's it's a stone carving which depicts
a hunting screen it's a scene of two
hunters and two animals and two sons two
sons in the sky now what does this mean
why are there two suns in the sky let's
take a look at what this means yeah so
these are not two sons it is the sun
indeed and it's a supernova a supernova
is an exploding star
so finding the signatures of exploding
Stars so about 50 years ago in the borza
Hama region of Kashmir in India
archaeologists uncovered a score Stone
carving of two Hunters a bull and two
beaming discs in the sky the carving was
pretty presumed to be a hunting scene
under a pair of Bright Stars at the
local Zenith but a team of
astrophysicists in India and Germany uh
had other ideas one by one they assessed
and ruled out various theories about the
origin of the scene
it was that it was an illustration of
the Sun and the Moon a pair of stars or
comets or asteroids in the sky one only
one Theory seemed to fit the evidence
the object depicted on the stone carving
appears to be the Supernova hb9 an
exploding star that Shone a hundred
times as brightly as Venus about 6500
years ago and if that is correct then it
is the oldest recorded evidence
observation of a Supernova by humans
all right so this is the oldest recorded
evidence of a supernova
by humans so that is one way to date how
old Indian astronomy is it's at least
6500 years old so people were observing
the night sky they were growing Star
Charts the animals depicted in that in
that scene are are not actual animals
these are constellations
constellations this seems to depict the
constellation of the hunter Orion most
likely yes uh so these are this is not
an actual animal it's it's a
constellation these two there's a dog in
this there's another animal that's been
being hunted
so it's a sky chart so Indians 6500 is
100 years ago we're drawing Sky charts
on rocks now um there's also the record
of the Greek
the Greek ambassador to India
meghastanis who was the ambassador of
the Greeks in in partly Putra during the
modern times yeah in in the court of uh
emperor chandragupta maurya so
megastinis recorded in his writings that
the Indians of that time
their reckoned time according to a
calendar that was called the saptashi
calendar that dated back to 6600
something BCE
600 something BCE that's more than 8 500
years before today
so Indians had been Reckoning time
through a proper calendar since from
about eight thousand five hundred years
before today
more than that and to create a proper
calendar is not easy
a calendar is based on the observations
of the night sky of the various
celestial objects especially the the
movements of the various solar system
objects the Sun the moon the various
planets all of that has to be studied in
in extraordinary detail to understand
the patterns and regularities of the
solar system of the entire system right
and it's based on that that you
understand
how long it takes for one year and what
are the divisions on that and that's how
you create a calendar and this calendar
was incredibly accurate it was better
than the calendar that is used today the
question calendar that we use today
so eight and a half more than eight and
a half thousand years ago Indians had
already created the world's best
calendar
so they must have been observing the
night sky and the solar system for
hundreds of years before that maybe
thousands of years before that so that's
how ancient Indian astronomy is and
whatever astronomical data the West
acquired
through through the Arabs was all data
that had been acquired from India right
for instance all the all the
astronomical data that was acquired that
was used by Johannes Kepler
to deduce his three laws of planetary
motion all of the data came from India
and so on so India is the birthplace of
science India is the birthplace of
mathematics of astronomy of calculus
of every
a philosophy of every meaningful Pursuit
Humanity knows it's all been acquired
appropriated from India it's been
repackaged with western names and today
we all Indians believe that the West is
the best in India has never been
anything which is completely wrong it's
because of our education system that we
are all misled like this there was a
time when even I must have made much of
this yeah
so uh please understand that India is
the birthplace of all the Sciences of
philosophy of history of writing of
astronomy of mathematics of the Sciences
of of of
pharmacology toxicology of botany
everything yeah India is the is the
original cradle of civilization and of
civilized thought
okay mother says what's the contribution
of sin towards Hinduism and why do the
people of present-day India consider sin
as an alien territory despite the fact
that since that sindha was once the
epicenter or of the Sindhu uh Saraswati
civilization
okay what's the contribution of sin
towards Hinduism see like mother says
Sindh was once the epicenter or the
center of gravity or whatever you want
to call it of the Sindhu Saraswati phase
of Indian civilization Indian
civilization transcends this into
Saraswati phase it's it's it goes back
before that
and even after this phase ended Indian
civilization still continued it still
continues today in a certain form
so when the Sindhu Saraswati phase of
Indian civilization was at its at its
peak synth was more or less to a large
extent the the center of of gravity of
the base because one of the Great Rivers
of one of the two great rivers of this
of this region was the Sindhu right the
other was a Saraswati which no longer
flows today
so as a consequence of that see
Saraswati phase of Indian civilization
was centered around the subtitas in the
region the seven Great Rivers in Western
and Northern India which encompassed
parts of Afghanistan uh it can Encompass
jamun Kashmir uh it encompassed all of
Pakistan and Balochistan and also uh
Punjab haryana Gujarat Rajasthan uh
parts of madhya Pradesh paths or
Northern parts of Maharashtra and all
that it was an enormous geographical
territory
and this was essentially one of the
cradles of Indian civilization the ganga
yamuna Valley region was also one of the
cradles of Indian civilization so um and
if you look at the archaeological
evidence from this region let's say
around the Sindhu River the various
archaeological sites you find a huge
amount of evidence of what we today
consider to be a Hindu cultural
artifacts you find swastikas you find
shivlingas you you find uh statuettes of
ladies with Vermilion in their forehead
you know monks indoor that thing you
find so many evidences of what you would
call Hinduism the the British
archaeologist who was the head of the
ASI at the time in the 1920s John
Marshall he said that the uh
the culture of this of the so-called
Harappan civilization was so
distinctively Hindu that it is scarcely
uh you can scarcely uh differentiate
from present day existing Hinduism so
that is the contribution of of the
Saraswati Sindhu region including Sindh
towards Hinduism yeah it was I wouldn't
call it the birthplace of Hinduism but
it's a place where Hinduism developed a
lot and flourished a lot I mean you find
yoga also there and so on yeah so so
very very culturally Rich region
and even after the the slow decline of
the Saraswati Hindu phase of Indian
civilization the place was still
inhabited the Sindhu still remained and
there were various great cities in the
region including Meena nagar which is
present-day Karachi yeah Meena nagar was
one of the uh centers one of the
capitals of the of the great Maha
chaturbas of India the Western satraps
including uh people like nahapana and
Josh tana and other great great Kings of
the region and so on so yeah Sindh has
contributed a lot it's been one of I
mean India is incomplete without synth
make no mistake about it India is
incomplete without Sindh
India is incomplete without the Sindhu
River the Sindhu river is one of the one
of the
unalienable and integral components of
Indian civilization Indian civilization
is incomplete without the region and the
in the Sindhu River so it is it is it is
unfinished business yes we will we will
obviously this is territory that is this
is ancestral territory of all Indians
yeah all Indians would have had
ancestors who lived in this territory
guarantee 100 percent
so this is ancient Indian Territory it
is our ancient Heritage and we will
reacquire it and and the people of the
region are our own people so it's not
like we will evict them or anything
we will reintegrate this territory with
India in the future when the time is
right
why do the people of present-day India
consider send it to be alien territory
well it's currently part of Pakistan
temporarily albeit but it's currently
part of Pakistan so people who have
grown up after the so-called
Independence after partition they would
see it as part of another Nation it's
it's but natural and because of our
education system in India doesn't teach
us the right things that's why we see it
as a foreign country Pakistan is not
Pakistan is not a foreign country
Afghanistan and Bangladesh in Sri Lanka
Etc are not foreign countries the people
are the same as us yeah
so it's a matter of time it's uh it's
the unfinished uh Legacy the unfision
finished business the leftover of
history and it will be taken care of by
maybe the current leadership maybe a few
future leadership and it will be done in
a way that's best for all people of the
region and all our brothers and sisters
who live in the entire Indian
subcontinent
so I don't see Sindh as alien territory
I am sure lots of other people do which
is unfortunate and it should not be the
case
all right let's take some other quick
questions what else do we have
is it really true that being vegetarian
or vegan is better than being a meat
eater the hmonger also conquered a
significant portion of Eurasia where
heavy meat and dairy consumers and so
where the yamnaya Invaders of Europe who
were on average six feet tall incredibly
strong and muscular does consuming meat
give you any advantage over just
vegetables see let's let's look at it
from a different perspective
the Mongols they're nomads
the Mongols were Nomads it was the the
they lived a nomadic lifestyle and they
lived in this Frozen part of Eurasia
where the temperatures go down to minus
30 or even worse in Winter and in summer
it must be like you know barely above
zero I know it's reasonably present in
summer maybe 10 15 degrees sometimes it
may be higher but that's a very brief
phase and very little grows in this
place you you will get even in in parts
of India like ladakh the only things
that grow in this region in these
regions are root vegetables like turnips
and potatoes and any onions you don't
get green vegetables there so if you are
a nomadic uh culture who would depend on
moving from place to place every every
few weeks or months there is no way for
you to grow vegetables and even if you
try to grow vegetables almost nothing
grows there except root vegetables so
the only way you can survive
and the only thing you can use for
subsistence subsistence is meat and
Dairy
so being nomads
the Mongols made sure that they ate lots
of meat and dairy because that's the
only thing that made sense for them
that's the only way they were able to
survive and prosper
and the same goes for the yamnaya the
yamnaya where the inhabitants of the of
the Eurasian step the step region the
the Kazakhstan from all the way from
Mongolia to the Ukraine
you know the Frozen Heartland the step
region of Eurasia so the yamnya
themselves mostly lived in this region
and there were also Nomads they were
horse riding conquerors they went from
place to place they never stayed in one
place too long yes and so they also they
had the same lifestyle and if you eat
large amounts of dairy and meat lots
lots of protein and if you have a very
vigorous lifestyle that's that's based
on on riding horses all day and
conquering and pillaging and doing
whatever Warriors and Nomads do then
obviously your body structure will adapt
as a as a result of that yeah I mean you
find skeletons in the ganga Valley in
India whose average height is six feet
one inches that's from 30 000 years ago
so even they may have had that sort of
Lifestyle
it's all about the lifestyle plus
genetics plus diet so it's not about
meat being better it's about meat being
the only thing that made sense to them
because that's the kind of Lifestyle
they lived so they had to travel long
distances every day and the only ready
food they had available to them was
their were their herds of livestock most
likely and that's why they're dependent
on that whether it's the yamnya or the
Mongols or the homes
or the horns maybe even the skitians you
know the kittens who today
many Indians would have some skeet and
ancestry the kittens themselves had
ancient Indian industry and so on so I
don't think consuming meat gives you any
major advantage about this vegetables
meat is like processed vegetables
because you know herbivorous animals eat
lots of vegetable vegetarian food
whether it's glass or whatever else and
that's converted into protein and all
the minerals Etc are are Incorporated in
incorporated into the protein and so on
that's how it is so if you are an
athlete if you're a bodybuilder you want
to put on muscle mass very quickly maybe
it makes sense to eat meat because
that's the shortest you know the
shortest time period for acquiring the
kind of protein that you would other
otherwise need to acquire over a long
longer period of time from vegetables
but vegetables too give you all the
proteins you need provided you know what
to eat in what way to eat it's a whole
science dietary science in athletics and
sports and all that so I overall
vegetables are I think they give you a
lot of fiber they're better for
digestion they give you lots of
phytonutrients and other things
I think the best kind of Lifestyle the
best kind of diet is a good amount of
protein you should fulfill your daily
protein requirements in a lot of
vegetables because vegetables are great
for for overall health for mental
Clarity for fighting of cancer and all
these things so yeah it depends like
that I I don't think there's anything
right or wrong about this sort of diet
or that sort of diet in Indian culture
in Hinduism it is indeed said that it is
morally better it's it's a it's a it's
it's a superior lifestyle not to eat
meat because you're not causing any harm
or any pain to other living beings but
even in Hinduism there's no taboo that
you cannot eat meat apart from beef
right so um it's not better it depends
on what results you want to achieve if
you want if you if you are 70 kilos
if your weight is 70 kilos and you want
to become a bodybuilder and you want to
reach the 85 kilo Mark in let's say 15
months then maybe it makes sense for you
to eat meat Perhaps Perhaps I'm just
saying perhaps that's one hypothetical
possibility but you could also acquire
the same protein through through legumes
or paneer or milk or whatever so there
are lots of different options available
there's no right way or wrong way
everybody's body is different
everybody's metabolism is different and
you have to over time understand your
body and what's best for it and do what
is best according to that that's what I
would say
right
somnath Abhishek says how was your
experience on the debate on the popular
News Channel so yeah a couple of few
days ago I was on a debate on uh on
Prime Time on the Republic TV with arnab
goswami the debate was about the legacy
of the great magnificent prime minister
of India the one and only Mr nehru and
yeah I think I was one of the first
people who spoke on the debate I spoke
for about two minutes I said what I had
to say and then the debate went in
various directions and I was able to
speak only once on the debate because
there are lots of people on that and
typically on these debates what happens
is that if you want to be heard you have
to kind of speak over other people
interrupt people and try to barge in and
all that and I I did not think it was
appropriate for me to do that
um at that point in time yeah I I did I
I had some more points I obviously you
know you all know what points I want I
would have wanted to make I was
definitely not able to make all the
points I was able to speak a bit about
the geopolitical implications in
geopolitical angle of Mr nehru's actions
there was more that I could have
obviously said I speak a lot but yeah it
was the first time in like two or three
years that I was in Republic I was in
Republic once before in 2019 during the
I think during the balakode airstrike or
something yeah
so yeah it's it's it was good to be back
on Republic it was a very brief
very brief involvement on my part just a
couple of minutes I did say
I did share a few thoughts I think it's
available on Twitter and other places if
you want to see it just a couple of
minutes
overall it was a good experience and
let's see how it is in the future yeah
okay let's take one more question
Henry Stevens says how to handle success
and appreciation well you would not be
asking me this question unless you have
become successful so first of all
congratulations on succeeding so when it
comes to success you need to understand
you need to have your own definition of
what is success these are the parameters
that would constitute success for me so
if I do this this and I get these
results then that is what I would
consider success so first of all when
you achieve those results that you are
hoping for that you should understand
that this is the definition from my
perspective of success secondly you have
to analyze how you were able to reach
that stage maybe in the past you've
tried and failed but now you've been
able to succeed so try to analyze what
process you followed and what steps you
took you know in order to be able to
achieve what you call success and then
try to try to make a process or system
of that so that you can repeatedly
achieve that success and then maybe you
can try to find ways of if you let's say
let's say it's about earning money let's
say hypothetically it's about earning
money let's say you're successful in
earning one lakh rupees so then you must
ask yourself how do I first of all
replicate this and earn the same amount
of money every month and then as a Next
Step how do I 10 times that so now that
I've been able to replicate this
regularly that I can succeed earning so
and so amount of money per month how do
I take it to the next next level how do
I make it twice that amount or 10 times
the amount and then lastly the thing is
that don't ever allow success to go to
your ego
go to your head some people they're like
oh yes I've arrived I'm the big deal now
that should never ever happen you should
treat success and you know there's this
famous quote that you should treat
success and failure as imposters they
are all temporary success will come and
go failure will come and go but you have
to remain who you are don't allow it to
affect you and change who you are and
don't allow it to make you an egomaniac
or whatever it is some people
you know success reveals people's
character
and uh
some people remain humble and they
remain grounded even after achieving
whatever it is that they call success
and some people the moment there is a
little whiff of success they became like
you know they they become all different
and they become egoistic and arrogant
and all that
so success it reveals who you you really
are so I would say that whatever happens
success or failure don't allow it to
affect you too much success comes and
goes failure comes and goes but if you
are able to succeed then understand how
you succeeded and try to replicate that
and then once you're able to replicate
that on demand try to understand how to
take it to the next level and never ever
allow it to affect you from an ego
perspective remain who you are remain
humble remain grounded and keep on
working because no matter how much you
succeed there will be hundreds maybe
thousands maybe millions of people who
have succeeded way way way more than you
have ever succeeded maybe if you've
succeeded at this level there will be
millions of people who succeeded 100
times bigger than you so don't allow it
to affect your ego stay humble stay
grounded keep working
and always have a big objective in mind
which you're working towards that's what
I would say I think we have gone uh Way
Beyond the two hour mark
let me take one or two
let me take one or two what do we call
it live chat questions
live chat questions
um um what do we have
Beast man says Indians need to focus on
execution not on speech Yes yes sir yes
Beast man you are absolutely 100 right
talk is just hot air talk doesn't matter
work work hard execute execute execute
work hard work smart keep on working and
ignore the words
right what else do we have was was Thor
fat
was Thor fat uh Thor was not fat Thor is
Indra the great God Indra nowadays
Indians look at Indra as this this
this funny character you know the god of
rain the God who sits in this Palace
around with the his his devoted
following around him but in the old days
during The Vedic days Indra was the
great God of War the mightiest of the
Gods the god who's who who defeated the
great sea serpent vritra so he was a
great warrior and he had two main
weapons one was the hammer which was
called vajjara which is a hammer which
is its physical object and the other
meaning of bajira is the Thunderbolt so
it has dual meaning in Sanskrit so the
hammer and the Thunderbolt the so this
was Indra the mightiest of all the gods
and Thor is nothing but Indra and so is
Jupiter so is Zeus these are nothing but
the same God and Thor was never fact
you watch this silly ridiculous movies
that that Marvel puts out these days
You're Gonna think God knows what but
yeah Thor was never ever ever
fat
all right
um
anything else do we have any other
interesting question
any other interesting questions thought
love and Thunder
uh have I did I watch can't I'm not sure
what's the pronunciation of this thing
is it kantara kantara I'm not sure I
haven't watched it I've had no time to
watch it
um I hear incredibly good things about
it I also hear some other perspectives
I'm not sure if I can find the time I
would like to watch it but I'm not sure
if that time is coming anytime soon
because my forthcoming week is going to
be very busy yeah
uh yeah
how to improve storytelling skills I
have no idea
um how do you improve storage selling
storytelling skills
um people tell me I'm a reasonably good
Storyteller I'm I have no idea I just
speak uh I'm sure you can deconstruct
storytelling into it's about maintaining
tension and not giving out the the not
revealing the big thing until the end I
suppose and then structuring the story
properly and ensuring that there is
always tension and there is always
suspense so that the people don't feel
bored I think that's the gist of it and
then it's all about practice practice
and see the audience's reaction the more
you practice the better you get and
obviously you need feedback from the
audience
and once you realize that the audience
is hooked and you are able to replicate
that again and again that's when you
have become a good storyteller
all right I think we are done for today
thank you very much all of you thank you
very much for all the questions for your
viewership
and uh let's keep doing this
in the future this coming weekend once
again I am not going to be doing a live
stream because I will be in Jaipur
participating in the uh annual session
of the Jaipur dialogues you can catch me
there I'll there will be live streams
from Jaipur so you can catch me on that
but next weekend no live streams and we
will resume the live streams on the
weekend after that so thank you very
much for everything until next time I
bid you a very good day a very good week
take care